《怪物史瑞克4》
Once upon a time, a long time ago,
很久很久以前
a king and queen had a beautiful daughter named Fiona.
有位国王和王后 他们有个美丽的女儿 菲奥娜
But she was possessed by a terrible curse.
但是她中了一个可怕的诅咒
By day, a lovely princess. By night, a hideous ogre.
白天还是美丽可人的公主 夜幕降临后就变成可怕的怪物
Only true love's kiss could lift her curse.
只有真爱之吻才能解除诅咒
So Fiona waited in a tower, guarded by a dragon, until the day
所以菲奥娜在一个被火龙看守着的高塔上等啊等
when her true love would arrive.
等待着真爱降临的那一天
But as the days turned into years,
可是日复一日 年复一年
the King and Queen were forced to resort to more desperate measures.
国王和王后只得孤注一掷
Whoa, there.
到了
I don't know about this, Lillian.
我不知道该不该这么做 莉莉安
Fairy Godmother said only true love's kiss could break Fiona's curse.
仙女教母说只有真爱之吻 才能打破菲奥娜的诅咒
I don't trust that woman, Harold. This may be our last hope.
我不信任那女人 哈罗德 这也许是我们最后的希望了
Besides, he does come highly recommended by King Midas.
而且麦德斯国王也确实极力推荐他
But to put our daughter's life in the hands of this... person?
但要把我们女儿的生活交给这个人?
He's devious. He's deceitful. He's, he's...
他很狡猾 不诚实 而且他...
Rumpelstiltskin!
烂皮儿踩高跷皮儿!
Mrs. Highness.
王后殿下
How do you do?
你...你好
Down, Fifi. Get down!
下去 飞飞 下去
As you can see, everything's in order.
正如你们所见 一切尽在掌握
So you'll put an end to our daughter's curse?
你真的可以结束我们女儿的诅咒?
And, in return, you sign the kingdom of Far Far Away over to me.
作为回报 你要把远得要命王国转让给我
- Lillian, this is madness! - What choice do we have?
- 莉莉安 这简直是疯了 - 我们还有别的选择吗
Fiona has been locked away in that tower far too long.
菲奥娜已经被锁在塔里太久了
It's not like she's getting any younger.
她的青春一去便不再复返
But to sign over our entire kingdom?
但拱手让出我们整个王国?
Well, if your kingdom's worth more to you than your daughter...
好吧 如果你的王国对你来说 比你的女儿更重要
Nothing is worth more to us than our daughter.
没有什么比我们的女儿更重要
Jump, Fifi, jump!
跳上来 飞飞 跳
Just sign it and all your problems will disappear.
只要签个字 一切问题都会化为乌有
Your Highness! The Princess! She's been saved!
陛下 公主 被救出来了!
Who saved her?
谁救了她?
No one would have guessed that an ogre named Shrek,
没人能想到一个咆哮声令人闻风丧胆的
whose roar was feared throughout the land,
名叫史莱克的绿怪
would save the beautiful Princess Fiona.
会救出美丽的菲奥娜公主
True love's kiss led to marriage and ogre babies!
一吻定情 他们结婚 还生了一堆绿怪宝宝
The kingdom of Far Far Away was finally at peace.
远得要命王国终于迎来了和平与安宁
Goody for them! And they lived happily ever after!
哦 他们还真美 还从此永远幸福快乐地生活着
Sir? You're gonna have to pay for that.
先生 你撕书要赔偿的
Maybe we could make a deal for it, little boy?
或许我们可以为此做个交易 小男孩
- Oh, I'm not a real boy. - Do you want to be?
- 噢 我不是个真的男孩 - 你想变成真的吗
Nobody needs your deals anymore, Grumpel Stinkypants!
没人需要你那些交易了 烂皮儿臭侏儒!
I wish that ogre was never born!
我真希望那绿怪从来没存在过
Wake up, Daddy, wake up!
醒醒 爸爸 起床
- Good morning. - Good morning to you.
- 早安 - 早安
Better out than in.
嗝打出来总比憋着好
That's my line.
那是我的台词
Did my little Fergus make a...
我的小费格斯是不是有点... 噢!
...big, grownup ogre stink?!
绿怪的超级大臭味啊
Oh, that's diabolical!
真是恶魔般的气味
And on your left, the lovable lug that showed us you don't have to
在左手边 可爱的大家伙告诉我们
change your undies to change the world!
你无须更换内裤来改变世界
I wonder what Shrek's up to in there.
很好奇史莱克在那干什么
Get in there. Get... Impossible to put on!
把脚伸进来 把脚... 这根本穿不上
OK, the dragon goes under the bridge, through the loop...
好了 穿过桥下 绕过火龙
...and finally, into the castle.
最后 抵达城堡
Play date!
来玩吧
∮ Regardless of spring, summer, autumn, winter. You just need to call me out ∮
∮ 不论春夏秋冬，你只需叫我一声 ∮
Then Shrek kissed the Princess.
然后史莱克吻了公主
She turned into a beautiful ogre and they lived...
她变成了美丽的绿怪 然后他们从此...
Happily...
永远幸福...
- Ever... - After.
- 快乐地... - 生活着
Look! A shooting star!
看 流星
So, what did you wish for?
你许了什么愿
That every day could be like this one.
每天都可以像今天这样
Come here, you.
过来 宝贝
Morning, Daddy.
早上好 爹地
Morning.
早上好
Better out than in.
嗝打出来总比憋着好
Did my little Fergus make a...
我的小费格斯是不是有点...
Cute. Real cute.
好 很好
This lovable lug taught us
可爱的大家伙告诉我们
you don't have to change your undies to change the world!
你无须更换内裤来改变世界
Play date!
来玩吧
Shrek! The outhouse is clogged up!
史莱克 厕所堵了
She turned into a beautiful ogre and they lived...
她变成了美丽的绿怪 然后他们从此...
- Happily... - Ever...
- 永远幸福... - 快乐地...
After?
生活着?
- Daddy, get up! - Morning.
- 爹地 起床 - 早安
- Better out than in. - This lovable lug...
- 嗝打出来总比憋着好 - 可爱的大家伙...
- Play date! - No!
- 来玩吧 - 不
Outhouse again!
厕所又堵了
Come on.
拜托
Undies!
内裤
Outhouse!
厕所
- Get up, get up! - And they lived...
- 起床 起床 - 然后他们从此...
- Happily... - Ever...
- 永远幸福... - 快乐地...
After.
生活着
(通缉令：悬赏绿怪)
Roar.
吼
Nice landing, baby.
漂亮的着陆 宝贝
Hey! Now remember, don't eat the valet.
记住 别再把服务员吃了
Happy birthday, ninos! Vamos a la fiesta!
生日快乐 小宝贝们 一起来狂欢吧
Hey, Shrek, Shrek!
嘿 史莱克 史莱克
Mr. Shrek, would you sign our pitchforks?
史莱克先生 能不能在我的杈子上签个名
And our torches?
还有我的火炬
Oh, man, you used to be so fierce!
哥们儿 你是那么凶猛
Yeah, when you were a real ogre!
是啊 当你还是个真正的绿怪时
A real ogre?
真正的绿怪?
Shrek, it's a sing-along. You've got to sing along!
史莱克 这是齐唱 你也得一起唱
- No, thanks. - Please? I'll be your best friend.
- 不了 谢谢 - 拜托 我是你最好的朋友
Why does being your best friend entail me doing everything I don't want to do?
为什么成为你最好的朋友就规定我 要做一切我不想做的事
Please, Felicia, not in Daddy's ear.
求你了 费利西亚 别对着爸爸的耳朵
Excuse me, Mr. Shrek?
打扰一下 史莱克先生
Could you do that ogre roar of yours for my son?
你能给我儿子表演一下绿怪的咆哮吗
He's a big, big fan.
他是个超级铁杆粉丝
Do the roar.
快咆哮
You know, I'd rather not. It's my kids' birthday party.
我最好还是不要咆哮了 这是我孩子们的生日派对
- Do the roar. - Honey?
- 快咆哮 - 亲爱的
Why don't you go check on the cake?
你怎么不去看看蛋糕呢
- Sure. - And don't forget the candles.
- 没问题 - 别忘了蜡烛
Hold still.
别乱动
Thanks for the pants, Muffin Man.
谢谢你给我做裤子 松饼匠
I always wanted chaps! Yee-haw! Giddy up!
我梦寐以求的牛仔裤 呀哈! 动起来
- Monsieur Shrek. - Howdy, Shrek!
- 史莱克先生 - 你好啊 史莱克
Your cake. Voila!
你的蛋糕 看!
- What is that supposed to be? - That's Sprinkles the Ogre!
- 那是什么鬼东西 - 这是绿怪大蛋糕啊
Isn't he cute? He looks just like you.
是不是很可爱 多像你啊
But happy. It's a party, Shrek. You gotta cheer up!
高兴点 这是派对 史莱克 开心点
I'm in a great mood, actually.
事实上我心情很不错
- Oh, I'm gonna lick me a rainbow! - Donkey!
- 噢 我要舔舔那个彩虹 - 驴子!
As long as you're not doing anything,
既然你没什么事做
how about one of those famous Shrek roars?
不如来个出名的史莱克咆哮
- Do the roar. - Let me set you straight, Butter Pants.
- 快咆哮 - 让我明白地告诉你 黄油裤小朋友
An ogre only roars when he's angry.
绿怪只有发怒时才咆哮
You don't want to see me angry, do you?
你不会想看到我发怒的吧
Do it.
那就怒一个
Hold it together. Just hold it together.
忍住 忍住
Daddy, he's getting away. Do something.
爸爸 他要走了 做点什么啊
Oh, good.
太好了
- What happened to the cake? - Trust me. It's an improvement.
- 蛋糕怎么回事 - 相信我 这样还好一点
- You licked it! - No.
- 你舔了它 - 没有
Just because you're an ogre, doesn't mean you have to eat like one.
你是个绿怪不代表你要像绿怪那样吃东西
Looks like you forgot the candles!
你似乎忘记了蜡烛
OK, just watch the cake. I'll go get them.
好吧 看着蛋糕 我去拿蜡烛
Watch the cake?
看着蛋糕?
- Where's the cake?! - We ate the cake.
- 蛋糕呢?! - 我们吃了
- Ya. - What?
- 对 - 什么
No, don't cry.
不 别哭
Hey! I believe you promised my son a roar.
嘿 你好像答应我儿子要咆哮的
- Do the roar. - Roar.
- 快咆哮 - 咆哮
- I don't like it. - Pigs, we need another cake.
- 我不喜欢 - 小猪们 我们要再找块蛋糕
- We ate the other cakes. - One roar, man.
- 我们把蛋糕都吃光了 - 咆哮 哥们
Hey, everybody! Shrek's gonna do his famous ogre roar!
大家注意 史莱克要表演他拿手的绿怪咆哮了
Not now, Donkey. Pigs, are there any cupcakes?
不是现在 驴子 小猪们 还有没有纸杯蛋糕
- We ate them, too. - They have lollipops.
- 我们也吃完了 - 还剩棒棒糖
No, I ate them.
不 我吃了
- You didn't share? - Well, you didn't share the croissants!
- 你没分给我们? - 你也没分羊角面包!
- Everything's gonna be OK. - Shrek, what's going on?
- 一切都会没事的 - 史莱克 怎么了
- Come on, Shrek, your fans are waiting! - Do the roar.
- 来吧 史莱克 你的粉丝都等着呢 - 快咆哮
We need the cake!
我们需要蛋糕
Cake! Cake! Cake!
蛋糕! 蛋糕! 蛋糕!
I love you, Daddy.
我爱你 爸爸
Everybody, I have found another cake!
大家注意 我刚找到了个蛋糕
Shrek? Are you OK?
史莱克 你还好吧
- Unbelievable. - Tell me about it! Those villagers...
- 难以置信 - 你来说说看 那些村民...
I'm not talking about the villagers, Shrek. I'm talking about you.
我不要说什么村民 史莱克 我要说的是你
Is this really how you want to remember the kids' first birthday?
你就打算这样来纪念孩子们的第一个生日吗
- Oh, great. So this is all my fault? - Yes. But you know what?
- 好吧 所以这都是我的错? - 是的 不过...
Let's talk about this after the party, at home.
派对之后再说吧 回家再说
You mean that roadside attraction we live in?
你是说那个路边的旅游景点吗
Step right up! See the dancing ogre! Don't worry! He won't bite!
快来看 跳舞的绿怪! 别担心 他不咬人
I used to be an ogre. Now I'm just a jolly green joke!
我曾经是个绿怪 而现在我只是个绿色小丑
OK, OK, maybe you're not the ogre you used to be.
好吧 也许你不是曾经的那个绿怪了
But maybe that's not such a bad thing.
但那也许不是什么坏事呢
I wouldn't expect you to understand. It's not like you're a real ogre.
我不期望你能理解 你又不是真正的绿怪
You spent half your life in a palace.
你一半的人生都是在宫殿里度过的
And the other half locked away in a tower.
另一半被锁在高塔里
Look, all I want is for things to go back to the way they used to be!
听着 我想要的是一切都变回原来的样子
Back when villagers were afraid of me, and I could take a mud bath in peace.
回到村民们都怕我 而我也可以在泥潭里好好洗澡的时候
When I could do what I wanted, when I wanted to do it!
回到我想做什么就可以做什么的时候
Back when the world made sense!
回到这世界还有意义的时候
You mean back before you rescued me from the Dragon's Keep?
你是指回到你把我 从火龙看守的高塔中救出来之前?
Exactly!
没错
Shrek, you have three beautiful children,
史莱克 你有三个漂亮的孩子
a wife who loves you,
一个爱你的妻子
friends who adore you. You have everything.
喜欢你的朋友们 你拥有一切
Why is it the only person who can't see that is you?
为什么你是唯一一个看不到这点的人
That's just great.
那可真是太好了
If she thinks I'm gonna slink back there and apologize,
如果她觉得我会溜回派对道歉
she's got another thing coming. She's not the boss of me.
她就别指望了 又不是什么都要听她的
I'm an ogre and I'm not gonna apologize for acting like one.
我是个绿怪 而我不会因为 像绿怪一样举止而道歉
Help, please! Someone, anyone at all, help me!
救命 有人吗 谁来救救我
Please, help!
拜托 救命
救命
I'm stuck! Help!
我卡住了 救命
Oh, please, help!
噢 救救我吧
Someone, anyone! Help me!
有没有人 救救我
The pain! I can see a bright light. A tunnel!
痛死我了 我都能看到天堂口的亮光了
Grandma? Is that you?
祖母 是你吗
Yeah, it's me, Granny.
对 是我 奶奶
An ogre! Please, Mr. Ogre, please don't eat me!
绿怪 求你了 绿怪先生 别吃我
I'm not gonna eat you.
我不会吃了你的
But you are an ogre... Aren't you?
但你是个绿怪啊 不是吗
Yeah, well, I... I used to be.
对 我...我曾经是
Look, move out or get crushed.
听着 出来或者被压死
So you're not gonna eat me?
所以你不会吃我咯
No, thanks. I already had a big bowl of curly-toed weirdo for breakfast.
不 谢谢 我早餐吃了一大碗卷脚趾样的怪东西
Wait up! What's your rush? Where you going?
等一下 干嘛这么急 你要去哪
Nowhere.
哪也不去
What a coincidence! I was just heading that way myself.
太巧了 我刚好也要走这边
But, seriously, let me give you a ride. I insist.
说真的 我顺路带你一程吧 我坚持这样
Come on. It's the least I can do after all you've done for me.
来吧 你帮了我 这是我唯一能做的
I got a hot rat cooking.
我可以做好吃的老鼠哦
All right! Can I interest you in a mudslide? Slug and tonic?
好了 你会对泥沼感兴趣吗 懒洋洋的 舒服的泥潭浴
A liquid libation to ease that frustration?
放松一下 舒缓沮丧的情绪
- Eyeball-tini? - Well, maybe just one.
- 眼球马蒂尼? - 好吧 我只能喝一杯
So the centaur says, "That's not the half I'm talking about."
半人马说 "这不是我想说的"
I gotta say, Shrek, I envy you.
我必须承认 史莱克 我很嫉妒你
To live the life of an ogre... no worries, no responsibilities.
过一个绿怪的生活 没有忧虑 没有责任
You are free to pillage and terrorize as you please.
你可以随心所欲地掠夺和统治
- Free? That's a laugh. - Oh, yeah?
- 随心所欲? 天大的玩笑 - 是吗
Sometimes I wish I had just one day to feel like a real ogre again.
有时我希望哪怕有一天 可以重新做回个真正的绿怪
Why didn't you say so?
你怎么不早说
Magical transactions are my specialty!
魔法交易可是我的专长
Great. Next to mimes, magicians are my favourite people.
真不错 除了哑剧演员 我最喜欢的就是魔术师了
Hold on.
稍等片刻
"King for a Month." "Knight for a Week."
"一个月的国王" "一星期的骑士"
Ogre for a day.
一天的绿怪
Think about it, Shrek. To be feared and hated.
考虑一下吧 史莱克 被人恐惧和憎恨
You'll be, like, "Roar!"
你可以这样咆哮
And the villagers will be, like, "Get away! It's Shrek! I'm so scared of him!"
然后村民们就会像这样 "快跑 是史莱克 好害怕"
It would be just like the good old days, when your swamp was your castle.
就像过去那些美好的日子一样 沼泽地就是你的城堡
- When the world made sense. - All right, what's the catch?
- 当世界都还有意义的时候 - 好吧 有什么条件
Catch? No. There's no catch. No catchings, really.
条件? 不 没有条件 真的
I mean, there's something. Small thing. Nothing. A little thing.
我是说 就有一点 小小的 小小的代价
All right, I knew it. So what do you want?
好吧 我就知道 你想要什么?
- A day. - A day.
- 一天 - 一天
Rat's done!
老鼠烤好了
To make the magic work, you gotta give something to get something.
要使魔法生效 你得付出才能得到
In this case, you gotta give a day to get a day. That's all.
就这件事来说 你得贡献出一天来得到一天 就是这样
I can't just pick up and leave my family.
我不能就那么丢下我的家人
But that's the best part, Shrek! It's a magical contract.
那就是最好的部分 史莱克 这是个魔法合约
No one will even know you're gone.
没有人会知道你不在
And by the time this day is up, you are gonna feel like a changed ogre.
然而等到这一天结束 你就会觉得像变了个人似的
Still, I don't know.
我还是有点犹豫
Hey, no problem. Forget it, no big D. Doesn't matter.
没所谓 别管它了 没关系
Do you like white meat or dark meat?
你想要胸肉还是腿肉
So what day would I have to give up?
那我要贡献出的一天是哪天?
I don't know, any day. A day from your past.
不知道 随便一天 你过去的一天
A day you had the flu? A day you lost a pet?
你得流感的那天? 你失去宠物的那天?
A day some meddling oaf stuck his nose where it didn't belong
某个多事的呆子插手他不该管的事
destroying your business and ruining your life?!
而搅黄了你的生意 毁了你的人生的那天?!
Just for an example.
只是打个比方
How about the day I met Donkey?
不如用我遇到驴子的那天吧
Now, there's a day I'd like to take back.
那会是我想收回的一天
I don't know who that is.
我不知道你说的是谁
I know. What about a day you wouldn't even remember?
我知道了 不如用你都不记得的一天
Like a day when you were a baby.
比如你还是个婴儿时的一天
- An innocent, mindless little baby. - Take any of those days you want.
- 一个无辜天真的小宝贝 - 那些日子你想拿就拿吧
- Take them all for all I care. - Oh, just one will do.
- 我才不管你拿走哪一天呢 - 唯有一天你会介意
OK, good. A day from your childhood it is.
很好 你童年的一天
I guess there's nothing wrong with wanting a little time for myself.
想要一点属于自己的时间总没错吧
Just 24 tiny little hours.
仅仅是短短的24小时而已
- I'm still my own ogre! - Yeah, you is!
- 我还是原来那个绿怪 - 对 没错
I never needed to ask for anyone's permission before.
我以前从不用请求任何人批准
So why start now?
所以现在干嘛要请求呢
Go on, Shrek.
来吧 史莱克
Sign it!
签吧
Go on, Shrek.
继续 史莱克
Sign it, Shrek! Sign it!
签吧 史莱克 签下你的名字
You signed it.
噢 你签了
So, tell me. What happens now?
告诉我 会发生什么
Have a nice day.
玩得开心
I think I fell on my keys.
我觉得我摔在钥匙上了
There are 40 children in that shoe,
那只鞋里有40个孩子
which is why the weasel goes pop to this very day.
所以黄鼠狼才这么猖獗
Oh, great.
噢 好吧
As we head over the river and through the woods...
我们马上就要过河 然后穿过森林...
Ogre!
绿怪!
Kill the ogre! Kill the ogre!
杀了绿怪! 杀了绿怪!
This is the part where you run away!
这个时候你们该逃跑了
Sure is great to be wanted again.
再次被通缉的感觉真是太好了
Nice one.
这张不错
Fiona?
菲奥娜?
Oh, no.
噢 不
My home.
我的家
Fiona!
菲奥娜
Fiona! Are you in there?!
菲奥娜 你在里面吗
All right, Rumpel!
好了 烂皮儿
This wasn't part of the deal!
这不是交易的一部分
Rumpel!
烂皮儿
Ogre!
绿怪!
We've got another one, ladies! Get him!
我们又找到一个 姑娘们 抓住他
Who are you?!
你们是谁
What are you doing in my swamp?
你们在我的沼泽地干什么
Looks like a troublemaker!
看起来有点棘手啊
Spread 'em!
扯!
Nice job, ladies!
干得漂亮 姑娘们
You witches are making a big mistake! I know my rights!
你们这些女巫正在犯大错 我知道我有什么权利
You have the right to shut your mouth!
你有闭嘴的权利
Donkey, stop with the singing, will you?
驴子 能不能别唱了?
Donkey!
驴子!
Donkey, where am I? What's happening?
驴子 我在哪 发生了什么
Quiet down there! Oh, I hate this song.
安静点 噢 我讨厌这首歌
I'm driving, so I'm in charge of the music.
我是驾车的 所以我来管音乐
Will you witches make up your mind?
你们这些女巫能不能想好了再让我唱
Donkey? What's going on? Do you know where Fiona is?
驴子 这是怎么回事 你知道菲奥娜在哪吗
Quiet, ogre! You're gonna get me in trouble and I need this job.
安静点 绿怪 别给我找麻烦 我需要这份工作
I am not going back to work for Old MacDonald.
我才不要回去给老麦唐纳打工
Tell me to E-l-E-l-O. "E-l-E-l-No!" That's what I said.
别跟我唱"咿呀咿呀哦" "咿呀咿呀不"这才是我要说的
Where are my babies? And where's your wife, Dragon?
我的孩子们都在哪 你老婆火龙呢
Look, I think you have me confused with some other talking donkey.
听着 我觉得你把我和别的会说话的驴搞混了
I've never seen you before in my life.
我以前从来没见过你
Never seen me before? Come on, Donkey!
从没见过我? 拜托 驴子
And how do you know my name anyway?
说起来你是怎么知道我名字的
It's me, Shrek. Your best friend?
是我啊 史莱克 你最好的朋友?
A donkey and an ogre friends?
驴子和绿怪是朋友?
That's the most ridiculous thing I ever heard!
这是我听过的最荒谬的事
Can you at least tell me where they're taking me?
那你起码能不能告诉我她们要把我带哪儿去
To the same place they take every ogre. To Rumpelstiltskin.
去她们带每一个绿怪去的地方 去见烂皮儿踩高跷皮儿
- Stiltskin! - I said quiet!
- 踩高跷皮儿! - 我说了安静点
Oh, no.
噢 不
It's time to crumble!
来赌博啊
Place your bets! Place your bets! We start tout de suite!
买定离手 买定离手 马上就开始
Yeah!
耶!
Gingy?
姜饼人?
Gingy snap!
姜饼人致命一击!
There's one!
又一个绿怪
Disgusting, filthy ogre!
恶心 肮脏的绿怪
Hideous monster!
邪恶的怪物!
Filthy, filthy creature!
肮脏的生物!
Disgusting creature!
令人作呕!
Move it!
快推!
Don't worry, Donkey. I'll get us our lives back.
别担心 驴子 我会把我们救出去的
Yeah, right. Put a little mustard on mine, Captain Crazy!
好啊 拯救我吧 疯子队长
Mr. Stiltskin?
踩高跷皮儿先生
You got another customer.
你又有个客户
- Wolfie! - Yes, Mr. Stiltskin.
- 狼外婆 - 是 踩高跷皮儿先生
Bring me my business wig.
把我的生意假发拿来
Mr. Stiltskin, please!
踩高跷皮儿先生 拜托你了
- OK, go. - Please make me a real boy!
- 好了 说吧 - 请把我变成个真正的男孩吧
Go away! Terms are in the details, balsa boy.
走开 细节都在条款里 木头男孩
Sayonara, termites! Hello, acne!
再见 白蚁们! 你好 粉刺!
Stiltskin!
踩高跷皮儿
Shrek!
史莱克
There he is!
你来啦
So close!
就差一点
Have I been waiting for you!
我等你等得花儿都谢了
Ladies, this is the guy that made all of this possible!
女士们 这就是使这一切成为可能的家伙
So, tell me, how are you enjoying your day?
来说说看 这一天怎么样
All right, Rumpel, what's going on? What have you done?
好了 烂皮儿 发生了什么 你做了什么
No, Shrek, it's not what I've done. It's what you've done.
不 史莱克 不是我做了什么 而是你做了什么
Thanks to you, the King and Queen signed their kingdom over to me.
多亏了你 国王和王后把王国转让给了我
They would never do that.
他们绝不会那样做
They would if I promised them all their problems would disappear.
他们会的 只要我承诺他们的问题都会化为乌有
And then they disappeared!
然后他们 化为乌有了
They would have done anything
他们会做任何事
if they thought it would end their daughter's curse.
只要是他们觉得能解除他们女儿诅咒的事
I ended Fiona's curse!
是我解除了菲奥娜的诅咒
How could you when you never existed?
如果你从来不存在 怎么去解除诅咒呢
You better start making sense, you dirty little man!
你最好把话给我说清楚 肮脏的小人
Here, let me spell it out for you!
来 让我一字一句跟你说清楚
You gave me a day from your past, a day you couldn't even remember.
你给了我你过去的一天 连你都不记得的一天
A day when you were an innocent, mindless little baby.
当你还是个无辜天真的小宝贝时的一天
You took the day I was born.
你把我出生那天拿走了
No, Shrek. You gave it to me.
不 史莱克 是你给我的
Enjoy this while you can, Stiltskin, because when this day is up...
趁还能享受尽情享受这一切吧.踩高跷皮儿.因为这天马上就过去了
But you haven't heard the best part.
不过你还没听到最精彩的部分
Since you were never born, once this day comes to an end, so will you.
既然你从来没出生过 当这一天结束 你也会消失
Where's Fiona?
菲奥娜在哪
Where's my family?
我的家人在哪
Silly little ogre. You don't get it, do you?
愚蠢的小绿怪 你还没听明白吗?
You see, you were never born.
你看 你从没出生过
You never met Fiona.
你从没遇到过菲奥娜
Your kids don't exist.
你们的孩子不存在
How's that for a metaphysical paradox?
这是个多哲学的悖论啊
Looks like you got exactly what you wanted!
看起来你刚好得到了你想要的
- Happy Ogre Day! - Rumpel!
- 祝你绿怪日快乐 - 烂皮儿!
Get him, witches!
抓住他 女巫们
You know what'd help morale around here? Flip-flop Fridays.
你知道什么能振奋人心吗 周五踢踏舞之夜
Feet be comfortable with the breeze on your toes.
漫不经心地舞动 放松你的脚趾
Come on, girls!
上 姑娘们
Lock all the doors, you worthless witches! Do it!
把所有的门锁起来 你们这些没用的女巫 快去!
I'll be right back, Donkey!
马上回来 驴子
I don't know you! I don't know him!
我不认识你 我不认识他
I'm glad I'm not you.
我很庆幸我不是你
Help me! Help!
救救我 救命
Help!
救命
No, not my pretty ball!
不 我漂亮的球球!
Watch out!
小心!
Wolfie?
狼外婆?
My angry wig.
拿我的怒火假发来
Help! I've been kidnapped by a deranged, unbalanced ogre!
救命啊 我被一个精神错乱的绿怪绑架了
Donkey! Get off of me!
驴子 别蹬我
Watch it with your pointy hooves!
当心点你的蹄子
- Just take my wallet! - Hey!
- 把我钱包拿走吧 - 嘿
I'm being ass-napped!
我他妈被绑架了
Animal cruelty! Help!
可怕的怪物 救命啊
You need to calm down!
你冷静点
I'm your friend.
我是你的朋友
I'm not gonna hurt you, all right?
我不会伤害你的 好吗
Good. I'm gonna let go...
好吧 那我现在...
...right... now.
...放手
Please! Eat my face last! Send my hooves to my mama!
求求你 最后吃我的脸 把我的蹄子寄给我妈妈
Donkey! You've got to trust me.
驴子 相信我
- Why should I trust you? - Because...
- 我凭什么相信你 - 因为...
Because...
因为...
OK.
好吧
∮ Regardless of spring, summer, autumn, and winter
∮ 不论春夏秋冬 ∮
∮ You just need to call me out
∮ 你只需叫我一声 ∮
∮ I will be by your side
∮ 我就会在你身边 ∮
∮ I am your friend
∮ 我是你的朋友 ∮
Fine! Go ahead! Run away! Who needs you?
好吧 跑吧 有多远滚多远 谁要你啊
I've never seen an ogre cry.
我从没看过绿怪哭泣
I'm not crying.
我没在哭
It's nothing to be ashamed of. I cry all the time.
没什么好害羞的 我还整天哭呢
Just thinking about my grandma, or thinking about baby kittens,
只要想起我的祖母 或者是小猫咪
or my grandma kissing a baby kitten, or a little baby grandma kitten.
或者我祖母亲吻小猫咪 或者小小猫咪祖母
- That is so darn sad. - I said, I'm not crying!
- 见鬼 这真悲催 - 我说了我没哭
Take it easy, I'm only trying to help.
放松点 我只是想帮忙
It's none of my business why you're upset.
你干嘛不高兴又不关我的事
By the way, why are you upset?
说起来 你干嘛不高兴
I was tricked into signing something I shouldn't have.
我被骗签了不该签的东西
You signed up for one of them time-shares, huh?
你不会是签了做苦力的卖身契吧
No. I signed this.
不 我签的是这个
You should never sign a contract with Rumpelstiltskin!
你永远不该和烂皮儿踩高跷皮儿签合约!
Yeah, I got that.
对 我现在明白了
- His fine print is crafty. - I know.
- 他精美的印刷下隐藏着狡诈 - 我知道
- His exit clauses are sneaky. - Yeah, I...
- 他的解约条款很隐蔽 - 对 我知...
- What did you say? - I'm talking about the exit clause.
- 你刚说什么 - 我在说解约条款
Used to be, you had to guess his name,
以前是你得猜出他的名字
but now everybody knows who Rumpelstiltskin is.
但现在所有人都知道烂皮儿踩高跷皮儿是谁了
Donkey, I've read the fine print.
驴子 我已经仔细看过合约了
There's nothing about an exit clause in here.
完全没提到有解约条款啊
Well, you didn't expect him to make it easy for you.
你不能期待他会让你轻易找到吧
Here, let me show you how it's done.
来 让我告诉你怎么找
I didn't spend all that time around them witches
我每天跟女巫们厮混
without picking up a few tricks.
可不是无所事事的
Your tiny, little ogre brain couldn't begin to comprehend
你的小容量绿怪脑瓜是不可能理解
the complexity of my polygonic foldability skills.
我折多边形的复杂技巧的
What are you doing?
你在干嘛
Hey, I can't get my origami on unless you back off.
嘿 你不离远点我没法折纸
Thank you. OK, here's what you gotta do. You fold this piece here,
谢谢 好了 这就是要做的 把这边折起来
make this letter match up here, bring this corner here,
让这个字母放到这 把这个角折上来
and if you do it just right, it will show you what to do. There!
如果你折对了 它就会告诉你怎么做 看!
"Try Lou's Bliss."
"试试露的幸福"
Who's Lou?
露是谁
Give me that!
给我
"True Love's Kiss."
"真爱之吻"
You have to take me to dinner first.
你得先请我吃晚饭
"According to fairy tale law, if not fully satisfied,
"根据精灵法则 如果对此不满意
true love's kiss will render this contract null and void."
真爱之吻会使这合约无效"
Donkey, you did it! Look at you!
驴子 你做到了 看看
If Fiona and I share true love's kiss, I will get my life back!
如果菲奥娜和我交换真爱之吻 我就可以重新回到我的生活了
OK! This isn't a petting zoo! So where is this Fiona?
好了 这又不是宠物乐园 那这个菲奥娜在哪
Well, that's just it, you see.
这就是问题所在
I don't know.
我不知道
You know, when I lose something, I always try to retrace my steps.
我丢了什么东西的话 就会沿着脚印一路找回去
So... where did you leave her last?
所以...你最后一次见她是什么时候
The last time I saw her,
我最后一次见到她时
I told her I wished I'd never rescued her.
我跟她说我希望从来没救过她
- Oh, no. - Shrek?
- 噢 不 - 史莱克?
Shrek! Shrek, wait! Wait, Shrek!
史莱克! 史莱克 等等! 等等 史莱克
What, are you crazy? That's the Dragon's Keep!
你疯了吗 这是火龙看守的
They keep dragons in there!
里面有火龙
OK, yeah, fine! Go ahead!
好吧 你就去吧
I'm gonna just hang back here and find us some breakfast!
我就在这等着 给咱俩找点早餐
Fiona!
菲奥娜
Oh, no.
噢 不
If I didn't save Fiona...
如果我没救菲奥娜...
...then who did?
...那会是谁救的呢
This is the favour Fiona was supposed to give me on the day we met.
这本该是我们相遇那天菲奥娜给我的礼物
It's a symbol of our love.
是我们爱的象征
Now smell it!
快闻闻
Hey, man, get that dirty favour out of my face!
嘿 哥们 把那脏礼物从我面前拿开
Your nose is the only chance I have of tracking down my wife,
你的鼻子是找到我妻子的唯一机会了
so stop complaining and start smelling.
所以别抱怨 闻闻看
Smell it! Get it! Away you go, girl!
闻一下 快闻 快点
Do I look like a bloodhound to you?
我看起来像只猎犬吗
In case you haven't noticed, I'm a donkey, not a dog!
如果你没看清楚的话 现在告诉你 我是只驴子 不是狗
If I was a dog, they'd call me Dog, not Donkey!
如果我是只狗 他们就会叫我狗 而不是驴子!
And another thing...
而且还有件事...
Wait a minute.
等一下
I think I got something.
我好像闻到了什么
- Whatever it is, it's sweet. - Fiona.
- 不管是什么 闻起来很香 - 菲奥娜
Luscious and tasty.
香甜可口的感觉
Hey! That's my wife you're talking about.
嘿 那可是我老婆
Donkey!
驴子!
Yeah! Waffles!
耶! 华夫饼
And I thought the Waffle Fairy was just a bedtime story.
我还以为华夫饼仙女只是睡前故事
Sticky stacks of golden, syrupy deliciousness!
层层酥脆金黄 刷着糖浆的美味!
Donkey! Don't eat that!
驴子 别吃
There's a stack of freshly made waffles in the middle of the forest.
树林中间摆着一摞刚出炉的华夫饼
Don't you find that a wee bit suspicious?
你不觉得这有点可疑吗
Oh, you... I'm just... What are you...?
噢 你... 我只是... 你要...
Bad Donkey! Mustn't.
这样不好 驴子 不许
I said, don't! Don't! No! Get away from it.
我说不 别吃 离开它
You did.
你还是吃了
Look out!
小心
Donkey!
驴子!
- Are you OK? - I'm fine.
- 你还好吗 - 我没事
Donkey.
驴子
Help! Help me!
救命 救救我
Help, Shrek! Help!
救命 史莱克 救命!
Watch your head.
小心头
Hey, it's a new guy!
嘿 有个新来的
Look at him, all dressed up in his Sunday vest.
.看看他 穿着周日小背心
He's really tiny, isn't he?
他长得真瘦小 不是吗
Yeah. Fate has delivered us a comrade-in-arms
对 感谢命运之神给我们送来了个亲密的战友
and for that, we are thankful. Suit him up!
给他穿上装备
- Let's go, greenie. - Now, wait a minute!
- 走吧 哥们 - 等一下
- Hey! - Here you go.
- 喂 - 不错嘛
- Welcome to the resistance. - Resistance?
- 欢迎加入反抗军 - 反抗军?
We fight for freedom and ogres everywhere!
我们为了自由 为了所有的绿怪而战!
I didn't know we could do that.
我从不知道我们还会这招
Help! You can't eat me! I got the mange!
救命 别吃我 我长了疥癣的
- I'm poisonous! I'm all poi... - I'll take him! This order's to go.
- 我有毒 我... - 让我来 这个我最拿手了
Hey! I haven't removed his giblets yet.
喂  我还没把他剖肠挂肚清干净呢
Trust me, you don't want to eat this one.
相信我 这不合你口味
I go down smooth, but come out fighting!
我会平静地进去 奋战着出来
- Let go! - Don't make Mama mad.
- 放手 - 别让老娘发火
Your dinner is my friend!
你的晚餐是我的朋友
- Come on, guys! - I got to get the giblets out!
- 别吵了 伙计们 - 我得先把内脏去了
- She's back. - There she is.
- 她回来了 - 她来了
Fiona!
菲奥娜
I'm so happy I found you!
我好高兴终于找到你了
Maybe you missed orientation,
也许你是跑错了方向
but for future reference, personal space is very important to me.
不过还是提醒你一句 私人空间对我来说很重要
You don't know who I am, do you?
你不知道我是谁吧
No.
不知道
Brogan, I have news from Far Far Away.
布洛根 我有远得要命王国的最新消息
Gather the others and meet me in the war room.
把大家召集起来 到军事室开会
Gretched, make sure everyone is prepared to move out tonight.
格雷琴 确保人员物资今晚前能准备好
- I need to talk to you. - What is it?
- 我要和你谈谈 - 你到底怎么回事
OK, I know you don't remember me, but...
好吧 我知道你不记得我了 不过...
...we're married. Hear me out.
我们是夫妻 听我说
And at the birthday party with some pigs and a puppet,
在生日会上 有几只小猪还有木偶
the villagers wanted me to sign their pitchforks,
村民们想让我在他们的杈子上签名
and this boy kept saying, "Do the roar."
还有个小男孩不停说 "快咆哮"
Then I punched the cakes that the pigs ate and the next thing I knew,
然后我砸了小猪们偷吃的蛋糕 然后等我醒了之后
my donkey fell in your waffle hole.
我的驴子就掉进了你的华夫饼陷阱
Right? Who's with me?
明白了吧 有人听懂了吗
I guess I must have kicked him harder than I thought.
我想我刚刚应该踢重一点的
Fiona, I need to...
菲奥娜 我必须...
Witches! All right, everyone, you know the drill!
女巫! 好了 所有人 你们知道我们怎么演练的
- Fiona! - Witches! Oh, no!
- 菲奥娜 - 女巫 噢 不
- Witches! Witches! - Come on, now.
- 女巫 女巫 - 过来吧
Fiona, that's the third patrol today. We can't hide forever.
菲奥娜 这是今天第三次巡逻了 我们不能躲一辈子
Trust me, Brogan. After tonight, we won't have to.
相信我 布洛根 今晚之后我们就不用躲了
- That's your wife? - That's my wife.
- 那是你老婆? - 那是我老婆
Well, I see who wears the chain mail in your family!
我能想象出在你们家谁是老大了
Some people like to look at the goblet as... as half empty.
有些人喜欢称酒杯空了一半
Me, I like to look at it as half full.
而我则喜欢说它满了一半
We've gone from the bottom to the top, ladies.
我们虽然有等级高低之分 女士们
But we're not just an empire.
但我们不仅是一个王国
We're a family.
我们是一家人
Everyone has got their cupcake? Cupcake, cupcake? Good. Yes? Baba?
每个人都有纸杯蛋糕了吗 蛋糕 蛋糕 很好 你有了吗 芭芭?
Good.
很好
Yeah, you know, we have put away a lot of ogres.
是的 我们抓到了不少绿怪
And so one got away. Who cares? It's not a big deal.
只是有一个跑了 不过谁在乎呢 又不是什么大事
It doesn't matter to me.
我反正无所谓
It's not like it's the end of the world.
又不是世界末日
Except... funny thing.
除了... 一些有趣的事
Now that I think about it, the ogre who got away is Shrek!
我想到逃跑的那个绿怪是史莱克
And if he shares a kiss with Fiona by sunrise,
如果他在日出前吻了菲奥娜
it is the end of the world! Our world!
那就是世界末日 我们的世界末日!
My empire!
我王国的末日!
But, as I was saying,
不过 正如我所说
I like to look at the goblet as half full.
我总是乐观地看待一切
Yelling makes me so parched.
大喊大叫让我口干舌燥
Would anyone care for some water? Wet your whistle?
有人想来点吗 润润喉
A clear, crisp, delicious glass...
晶莹剔透的玻璃杯里
...of agua purificada?
斟满甘甜的泉水?
Anybody's thirsty? Nobody's thirsty? No?
有人口渴吗 没人口渴? 没人吗
Well, then does anyone care to tell me
好吧 那有人愿意告诉我
what it's going to take to get this ogre? You.
抓住绿怪需要什么 你说说
Faster brooms?
更快的扫帚?
- No! - Pointier hats?
- 错 - 更尖的帽子?
- No! You! - Maybe we could hire a professional bounty hunter?
- 错 你! - 或许我们可以雇一个职业赏金猎人?
What a world! What a world!
天啊 这是什么世界
You know, actually not a bad idea. Baba!
事实上这是个不错的主意 芭芭!
I need a bounty hunter.
给我去找个赏金猎人
And if music doth soothe the savage beast...
如果音乐能安抚那些凶残的野兽
...then I think I might know just the person!
我想我有个合适的人选
Listen up, everyone. Word has come from Far Far Away.
听好了各位 远得要命王国有消息说
Stiltskin is leading tonight's ogre hunt himself.
踩高跷皮儿要亲自指挥今晚的绿怪围捕
- He's never done that before. - What? Why?
- 他从来没这么做过 - 什么? 为什么
I bet that's because of us.
我打赌是因为我们俩
If that cupcake-eating clown
如果那个纸杯蛋糕小丑
finally leaves the safety of his filthy witch nest...
终于脱离了他那些肮脏女巫的保护
...he'll be vulnerable.
他一定会很脆弱
The plan's simple. If they follow the usual patrol route,
计划很简单 如果他们按照正常的巡逻路线
they'll reach the river by midnight.
就会在午夜的时候到达河边
We'll be concealed along this road, waiting for his caravan.
我们可以埋伏在路旁 等着他的篷车
Once they reach the clearing, I'll give the signal.
一旦他们到达空地 我就会发出信号
And then we attack!
然后就进攻
And when the smoke clears... Wait, what's this?
然后等烟雾消散后... 等等 这是什么
That's my chimichanga stand.
那是我的烤香肠摊
No, Cookie. We won't be needing that.
不 甜饼 我们不需要这个
Trust me, Fiona. Y'all gonna be really hungry after this ambush, OK?
相信我 菲奥娜 你们伏击完之后一定会很饿
Go and finish your little speech.
继续说你的计划
All right, as I was saying, when the smoke clears,
好吧 正如我所说 等烟雾散去后
Rumpelstiltskin is gone and the chimichangas have been eaten.
烂皮儿踩高跷皮儿完蛋了 烤香肠也吃完了
Far Far Away will finally be free.
远得要命王国就能重获自由
- And so will we. - Spread the word.
- 我们也会获得自由 - 传令下去
We move out as soon as Rumpel leaves the palace.
烂皮儿一离开宫殿 我们就准备行动
- Man, this is serious! - Tell me about it.
- 伙计 这下可有大事了 - 告诉我
How am I ever gonna get her to kiss me before sunrise?
我该怎么做才能让她在日出前吻我
Actually, I was talking about the revolution.
事实上我在说革命的事
Revolution?
革命?
Why don't you just tell her what you told me?
为什么你不把跟我说的话跟她说一遍
About how you're her true love and you came from an alternate universe.
关于你是她的真爱 以及你来自另一个时空之类的
Well, while I'm at it, why don't I tell her
如果我能那么做的话 我为什么不告诉她
that you're married to a fire-breathing dragon
你和一只会喷火的龙结婚了
and you have little, mutant donkey-dragon babies.
然后有了小小的变种驴龙杂交宝宝
I do?!
我真这么做了?
You saw what happened. She's gonna think I'm crazy.
你也看到刚刚的事了 她会觉得我疯了
I'm a daddy?
我成爸爸了?
You know what? If I got Fiona to kiss me once...
如果我能让菲奥娜亲我一次
...then I can do it again.
那我肯定能让她再亲第二次
Shrek, do my babies have hooves or talons?
史莱克 我的宝宝们长的是蹄子还是爪子
Donkey...!
驴子 嘘
Hello?
有人吗
Fiona?
菲奥娜?
You should not be here, senor.
先生 你不该出现在这里
Puss?
靴猫?
You've gotta be kidding me.
这一定是开玩笑呢吧
Feed me, if you dare.
有种 就来喂我
Puss, what happened to you? You got so fa...
靴猫 你怎么了 你怎么变得这么肥...
- Fancy... - Do I know you?
- 非常帅... - 我认识你吗
Well, where's your hat? Where's your belt?
你的帽子呢 皮带呢
Your wee little boots?
你的小靴子呢
Boots? For a cat? Ha!
靴子? 猫穿靴子? 哈哈
But you're Puss in Boots.
但你是穿靴子的猫啊
Maybe once.
也许曾经是
But that is a name I have outgrown.
但那已经是我不能承受之名了
That's not the only thing you've outgrown.
那可不是你唯一不能承受的东西
Hey! I may have let myself go a little since retirement,
喂 我退休后也许是放纵了一点
but hanging up my sword was the best decision of my life.
但放下刀剑绝对是我此生最明智的决定
I have all the cream I can drink and all the mice I can chase.
我可以随心所欲地喝牛奶 抓老鼠
I'll get him later.
一会儿再抓它
Puss, what have I done to you?
靴猫 我对你做了什么
You've gone soft.
你变得软弱不堪的
Well, I do get brushed twice a day.
我一天刷两次毛
Look, it's not too late to fix it.
听着 现在补救还来得及
All you have to do is help me get a kiss from Fiona.
你只需要帮我从菲奥娜那里得到一个吻
What are you doing? Can I help you with something?
你在干嘛 有什么事吗
Well, I know how stressful mounting a rebellion can be...
我知道组织一场叛乱有多大的压力
...rallying the troops, planning attacks,
募集部队 计划进攻
so I brought you a little something to ease the tension.
所以我给你带了点小东西缓解压力
A gift basket?
礼物篮?
You're welcome. So let's see what you got.
不客气 看看都给你准备了什么吧
Heart-shaped box of slugs.
心形盒子装的肥蛆
Skunk-scented candle.
臭鼬味香薰蜡烛
- Look, this really isn't the... - What's this? Coupons!
- 不过现在不是时候... - 看这是什么 优惠券!
Let's see, "Good for one free foot massage."
看看 "专享免费足疗"
"A mud facial!" Oh, and here's one...
"沼泥美容" 噢 还有这个
"Good for one free kiss." Let's cash it now.
"专享免费香吻" 现在就兑现吧
Look, I don't know what this is all about,
听着 我不知道这是怎么回事
but I'm trying to run a revolution.
但我正要进行一次革命
So unless you have Rumpelstiltskin's head in there,
所以除非你能把烂皮儿踩高跷皮儿的人头带来
I suggest you take your gift basket,
我建议你还是拿着你的礼物篮
get out of my tent and go make yourself useful!
离开我的帐篷 去干点有用的事
Wow. You're right. I am sorry.
对 你说得对 我很抱歉
I was just trying to be friendly. No hard feelings?
我只是想表示下友好 没什么不好的感觉吧?
An apologetic hug?
歉意的拥抱?
And a quick kiss goodbye.
再来个晚安亲吻
Hey!
喂
Wait! Is that mistletoe I see?
等等 那个是不是槲寄生
Hey, Shrek! Are my babies cute, or do they make people feel uncomfortable?
嘿 史莱克 我的宝宝可爱吗 它们有没有让人觉得不舒服
- Where'd we find that guy? - Could it be true?
- 那家伙到底从哪冒出来的 - 是真的吗
Have the years of prim and pampery made me soft?
多年的安逸和娇纵使我软弱了吗
Don't be silly. Now who's a pretty kitty?
别傻了 谁是最美的猫咪
I am.
我
Daddy thinks you look real nice, Fifi.
爸爸觉得你看起来很美 飞飞
Honk.
嘎嘎
All right, Piggies, be gone!
好了 小猪们 走吧
Don't forget to take her little potty box with you.
别忘了带走她的小夜壶
This little piggy wants to go home!
小猪只不过想回家而已
- Mr. Stiltskin! He's here. - Nice.
- 踩高跷皮儿先生 他来了 - 很好
Pied Piper. How was your commute?
吹笛人 旅途还愉快吗
Good.
很好
You call this guy a bounty hunter?
这人也算个赏金猎人?
What's he gonna do, flute those ogres a lullaby?
他打算怎么做 给那些怪物吹摇篮曲吗
OK, got it!
好了 我知道了
Make it stop!
停下!
All right, that's enough.
好了 够了
Looks like it's time to pay the piper.
看来是该给吹笛人赏金的时候了
Griselda, seriously, it's time to pay the piper.
格里泽达 没听见吗 要给人家赏金了
Now go get my cheque book! Go! Move! Get out!
快去拿我的支票簿 快! 滚开!
Things are getting real sloppy around here!
你们这些不干事的
Here, now make sure they eat up!
给 确保他们都吃光光
You can't end tyranny on an empty stomach! Go on! Go!
不能空着肚子打仗 去 快去
Din-din!
叮叮
- Come on, Donkey. - One more time, please?
- 来吧 驴子 - 再来一次吧 拜托了
All right, but this is the last time.
好吧 但这是最后一次
Here it comes. Look at him.
这就来了 快看他
I see you!
我看见你们了
That's quite a friend you've got there.
你这个朋友真有意思
I can see why you haven't eaten him.
我知道你为啥没把他吃掉了
Donkey! I hate to pull you away from your adoring public,
驴子 我不想把你从这群喜欢你的人里拖走
but I'm not getting anywhere with Fiona.
但我和菲奥娜毫无进展
- I need your help! - Hey, everybody. Who wants dessert?
- 我需要你的帮助 - 嘿 伙计们 谁要点心
- Where'd you get these? - Fiona's garbage.
- 你从哪弄来的 - 菲奥娜的垃圾桶里
Just another gift from some clueless lover boy.
又是某个纯情单相思小男孩的礼物
That's a good one, Cookie!
这个很好笑 甜饼
Anyone who knows Fiona knows this stuff ain't gonna work on her.
认识菲奥娜的人都知道这种东西对她没用
Works on me.
对我有用
Donkey, what am I gonna do? It's like I don't even know her.
驴子 我该怎么办 我都不认识她了
You in trouble, Romeo. The only thing Fiona cares about is her cause.
你陷入麻烦了 罗密欧 菲奥娜只在乎她的事业
- To the cause! - To the cause!
- 为了事业 - 为了事业
All right!
好
Hello!
你好啊
- Nice moves. - What are you doing?
- 好身手 - 你要干什么
What does it look like? I'm getting ready for ambush action.
你以为我要干什么? 我是来为伏击做准备的
Oh, yeah. I always like to quad my lutes
我热爱战斗
and do some scrunches before an operational... op.
行动前要先热热身嘛
This one taken?
这个有人用了吗
We use that to clean the toilets.
那是用来刷马桶的
And we use that one to clean the thing we clean the toilets with.
这是我们用来刷马桶刷的
I knew that.
我知道
There you go, chief.
终于拿对了
Hey... Scott?
嘿 呃 斯科特?
My name is Shrek, actually.
事实上我叫史莱克
You're going to get yourself killed at the ambush tonight.
今晚的伏击你会丧命的
I'll be fine. I think I can take care of myself...
我没事的 我能照顾好自己
Well, let's see about that.
那就试试看
Hey! Hey... Hey!
嘿 喂
What the...?
怎么...
Fiona?
菲奥娜?
I got it.
我来
Give me your hand.
把手伸出来
The dragon goes under the bridge,
穿过桥下 绕过火龙
through the loop and finally...
绕过火龙 最后...
Into the castle.
抵达城堡
Wow.
哇哦
OK. Good.
好吧 好了
It seems like you can handle yourself.
似乎你确实可以照顾好自己
- But, Fiona... - Go get ready for the mission!
- 但菲奥娜... - 快去为行动做准备
- I will, but Fiona... - That's an order!
- 我会去的 但菲奥娜... - 这是命令
All right, let's get those axes sharpened and weapons packed!
好了 削利斧头 准备好武器
Preparation is half the battle!
完美的准备是打胜仗的一半
Ogre! Un momento! Un momento!
绿怪 等一下 等一下
Ogre, ogre, un momento!
绿怪 等一下
Just give me a minute.
给我一分钟
Look, Puss, I'm a little pressed for time.
靴猫 我现在心情不是太好
I am not believing what I have just witnessed.
我不敢相信我刚刚看到的
Back there, you and Fiona.
刚才在那儿 你和菲奥娜
There was a spark... a spark inside her heart
她心中有...有火花
I thought was long extinguished.
我以为早就熄灭了的火花
It was as if, for one moment, Fiona had actually found her true love!
好像 有那么一刻 菲奥娜真的找到了她的真爱
I am her true love. I ended her curse.
我就是她的真爱 我解除了她的诅咒
You know of her curse?
你知道她的诅咒?
By day, one way, by night another.
白昼与黑夜交替更迭
This shall be the norm.
只有噩梦轮回
Until you find true love's first kiss...
唯有真爱之吻
...and then take love's true form.
才能引向真爱之魂
You even know the little rhyme!
这首诗你都知道
It is true! You are the one! You must prove it to her!
绝对是 你就是真命天子 你要向她证明!
- How? - Convince her!
- 怎么证明 - 说服她
Go to her when she is alone
等她一个人的时候去找她
and tell her something that only her true love would know.
然后告诉她只有她的真爱才会知道的事
Know about what?!
知道什么事
Whoa! That's a whole lot of kitty! Shrek, can we keep him?
哇 好可爱的猫咪 史莱克 我们能养他不
Excuse me. Coming through!
对不起 借过一下
Pardon me, guys! Watch your back.
不好意思 注意身后
Look, Donkey, the chimichanga cart! Quick!
看 驴子 烤香肠摊 快
Andale! After him, burro! Donkey, vamonos!
闪开 跟着他 快 驴子
Man, you are a cat-astrophe!
伙计 你真是个灾猫难
And you are ri-donkey-Ious!
而你真是荒驴谬
I'll scout ahead. Wait for my signal.
我去前方侦察 等我的信号
Secure your positions!
各就各位
- It's quite a view from up here. - What are you doing?!
- 这里视野真好 - 你在这干嘛?!
Get back in position!
快回去就位
You need to know, once and for all, who I really am.
你必须知道我是谁
You are going to ruin everything!
你要毁了一切
Ruin everything? Actually, I'm gonna fix everything...
毁了一切? 事实上我是来拯救一切的
The ogres, Rumpel, your curse.
绿怪 烂皮儿 你的诅咒
How do you know about my curse?!
你怎么会知道我的诅咒
OK, OK, please, Fiona... Just hear me out.
好了好了 拜托 菲奥娜... 听我说
I can explain everything.
我可以解释这一切
- Where's Fiona's signal? - What's she waiting for?
- 菲奥娜的信号呢 - 她在等什么
- He's going to get away! - No, he's not.
- 他要跑了 - 不 他不会
Listen, I don't know who you are or how you know about my curse,
听着 我不知道你是谁 也不知道你是怎么知道我的诅咒的
but if any of these ogres find out I'm...
但如果这些绿怪发现我是...
- A beautiful princess? - That is not who I am! Not anymore.
- 一个美丽的公主? - 我不是 再也不是了
- Look, I know you're upset. - You don't know anything about me.
- 听着 我知道你很沮丧 - 你什么也不知道
I know everything about you.
我什么都知道
I know you sing so beautifully that birds explode.
我知道你的歌声可以让鸟儿都羞愧
- Big deal. - I know that when you sign your name,
- 这很了不起吗 - 我知道你每次签名时
- you put a heart over the "I". - So what?
- 都会在"I"上画个爱心 - 那又如何
I know that when you see a shooting star,
我知道你看到流星时
you cross your fingers on both hands,
会交叉手指
squinch up your nose and you make a wish.
捂着鼻子 许下愿望
I know that you don't like the covers wrapped around your feet,
我知道你睡觉时喜欢脚露在外面
and I know that you sleep by candlelight
我还知道你要点着蜡烛睡
because every time you close your eyes...
因为每当你闭上眼睛...
...you're afraid you're gonna wake up back in that tower.
你害怕会发现自己在高塔中醒来
But, most importantly, Fiona...
但最重要的是 菲奥娜...
...I know that the reason you turn human every day...
我知道你每天变样子的原因
...is because you've never been kissed...
是因为你没有被我...
...well...
呃
...by me.
吻过
- You move fast. - It's not me doing the moving.
- 你动作真快 - 这不是我要做的
- Why is this happening?! - Love?
- 这是怎么回事 - 爱情?
- No, I'm being forced to dance! - By love!
- 不 我被强迫着跳舞了 - 被爱情所强迫
No, I can't stop myself!
不 我停不下来
Please! Make it stop!
拜托 停下来吧
I can't control myself!
我不能控制自己
Yeah! Cookie's bringing the heat out of the kitchen!
耶 甜饼热浪冲出厨房 席卷世界了
Oh, no! It's the Piper!
不 是这个吹笛人
I can't believe I let this happen, and it's all because of you!
我不敢相信我让这样的事发生了 而这都是因为你!
- If you'd just let me kiss you! - What? You're insane!
- 只要你让我吻你 - 什么 你疯了吗
We must do something before they fandango themselves into oblivion!
我们必须做些什么阻止他们这样乱跳下去
- What can we do? - First, you must stop dancing!
- 我们能做什么 - 首先 你别跳了
When somebody tooties that fluty, I got to shake my booty!
只要有人吹起长笛 我就想摆动身体
Then it's up to me!
那就别怪我了
Hurry! We must get them away from the music!
快 我们得让他们离开这音乐
Puss and Donkey to the rescue! We saved the day!
靴猫和驴子拯救世界!
Donkey... Can I borrow your tongue?
驴子 我能不能借你舌头一用
Say what?!
你说什么
No. Hell...
不 见鬼...
I don't care how big your eyes get, player, it's not going down.
我可不管你有多大的眼睛 那对我没作用
All right!
好吧
Stop!
等等
- Where are you going? - To save my friends.
- 你要去哪 - 去救我的伙伴
- How, by getting yourself killed? - If that's what it takes.
- 怎么救 让你自己丧命吗 - 如果必须这样的话
Puss, say something.
靴猫 说点什么
- Puss? - Let me explain.
- 靴猫? - 我可以解释
That's how you knew so much about me.
所以你才知道我这么多事的吧
- Fiona, wait! Kiss me. - What?
- 菲奥娜 等等 吻我 - 什么
It's the only way to save your friends.
这是救你伙伴的唯一方法
Get out of my way.
别挡路
You used to believe that a single kiss could solve everything!
你以前是相信只要一个吻可以解决一切的
I don't understand. This doesn't make any sense.
我不懂 这完全不对劲
True love's kiss was supposed to fix everything!
真爱之吻应该是可以挽回一切的
Yeah, you know, that's what they told me, too.
对 他们也是这么跟我说的
True love didn't get me out of that tower.
让我逃出高塔的不是真爱之吻
I did. I saved myself.
是我 我救出了自己
Don't you get it? It's all just a big fairy tale.
你不明白吗 这就是个童话
Fiona, don't say that. It does exist!
菲奥娜 别这么说 那是真的
How would you know?
你怎么知道
Did you grow up locked away in a dragon's keep?
你是在火龙的看守下长大的吗
Did you live all alone in a miserable tower?
你试过在悲惨的高塔里孤独地生活吗
Did you cry yourself to sleep every night,
你试过每夜啜泣着入睡
waiting for a true love that never came?!
等待永远不可能到来的真爱吗?!
But... But I'm your true love.
但...但我是你的真爱啊
Then where were you when I needed you?
那我需要你的时候你在哪
Maybe you kissed her wrong?
或许你亲错人了?
No.
不
The kiss didn't work...
那个吻没起作用
...because Fiona doesn't love me.
是因为菲奥娜不爱我
Don't despair, fellow ogres!
不要绝望 绿怪兄弟们
They can put us in cages, but they can't cage our honour!
他们可以用笼子锁住我们 但不能锁住我们的荣耀
Shrek and Fiona are together?!
史莱克和菲奥娜在一起?!
Yeah, I've heard enough of your toot-a-lee-toots! You blew it!
我听够你的"嘀嘀嗒嗒"了 别吹了
Wolfie! My speech wig.
狼外婆 拿我的演讲假发来
Baba! Ready my makeup. And Piper, pull my socks up.
芭芭 给我化妆 还有吹笛人 给我穿袜子
- Tight. - Attention, citizens.
- 够紧 - 注意 居民们
Please stay tuned for a message from our tyrannical dictator!
请注意听我们的大独裁者发表演说
Hello, people. It is I, Rumpelstiltskin...
亲爱的臣民 是我 烂皮儿踩高跷皮儿...
...shepherd of your dreams.
你们梦想的守护者
Recently, a certain somebody
最近 某人...
has jeopardized our joyous lives.
正在威胁我们幸福快乐的生活
And that somebody is the rat-munching ogre called Shrek!
而那个某人就是丑陋的绿怪史莱克!
That is why I come to you, dear citizens.
所以我要向你们求助 亲爱的子民
For whomever brings me this ogre,
不论是谁把这个绿怪带给我
shall receive the deal of a lifetime.
他将得到一份终身快乐合约
Just think of it! Total and
想想吧
- complete happiness. - Ya!
- 无尽的快乐 - 耶
Dazzling, radiant fulfilment! All your greatest wishes.
所有的热情 欲望 一切愿望
- Yeah! - Your wildest dreams.
- 耶! - 最狂野的梦想
Anything you could ever want! No strings attached!
所有你想要的一切 没有任何附加条件
But hurry, this is a limited time offer.
不过要快 这是有时限的哦
So light your torches, sharpen your pitchforks and get your mob on!
点亮你的火把 削尖你的杈子 抄起你的拖把吧!
Shrek! Shrek! Shrek!
史莱克! 史莱克! 史莱克!
Go back where you came from!
回你的老家去
It seems that we are safe.
我们似乎安全了
Yeah, it looks a lot less pitchforky and torchy out there. Let's go.
让他们折腾去吧 我们走
What's the point? The kiss didn't work. It's over.
有什么意义 吻不起作用 一切都结束了
Look, Shrek, I know things might seem a little bleak right now,
听着 史莱克 我知道事情有点不尽如人意
but things always work themselves out in the end, you'll see.
但船到桥头自然直
- I bet by this time tomorrow... - Don't you understand?
- 我打赌明天这个时候... - 你不明白吗
There is no tomorrow.
没有明天了
There's no day after that, and there's no day after that day after that!
没有后天 没有大后天 没有大大后天
My life was perfect and I'm never going to get it back!
我的生活曾经是完美的 而我再也回不去了
If your life was so perfect, why'd you sign it away to Rumpelstiltskin?
如果你的生活真那么完美.那你干嘛还跟烂皮儿踩高跷皮儿签约
Because I didn't know what I had until it was gone! All right?
因为我直到失去了才知道它有多美好
I didn't know what I had.
我不知道它那么美好
Surrender now! I'm taking you in!
投降吧 我要把你带走
Don't try to fight it, ogre! The reward is mine!
别想抵抗 绿怪! 奖赏是我的了
Gingy?
姜饼人?
- You unhand me, green devil! - What are you doing?
- 放开我 绿魔鬼 - 你在干嘛
Collecting my bounty!
拿酬劳!
- Bounty? - What are you talking about, cracker?
- 酬劳? - 你在说什么 小饼干
Rumpelstiltskin promised the deal of a lifetime
烂皮儿踩高跷皮儿许诺给把你抓住的人
- for whoever could bring you in. - Deal of a lifetime?
- 一份终身快乐合约 - 终身快乐合约?
Where all your wishes come true.
你所有的愿望都可以实现
Wait a minute.
等等
- I can still fix this. - How you gonna do that?
- 还有得补救 - 怎么补救
You know what? I'm gonna give Rumpelstiltskin exactly what he wants.
我要给烂皮儿踩高跷皮儿他想要的
OK, Gingy, tell me about this...
好了 姜饼人 告诉我...
Were you going to eat that?
你们不是打算吃了他的吗
Not Shrek. That is not Shrek. Also not Shrek.
不是史莱克 这不是史莱克 这也不是史莱克
That's not even an ogre, it is a troll! Nice try.
这连个绿怪都不是 是个巨人 亏你们想得出来
- And that... - Roar.
- 还有这个... - 咆哮
...is just sad.
真是可悲
And what is that supposed to be?
这又是个什么鬼东西
I'm just a frightened old man.
我只是个吓坏了的老头儿
Don't listen to him! These ogres are crafty!
别听他的 这些绿怪都很狡猾
That is your father painted green.
那是你涂绿了的老爸
No, it's Shrek! Honest!
不 这是史莱克! 真的
Take them away!
让他们滚
Can no one bring me Shrek?! Where is he?
就没有人能抓到史莱克吗?! 他在哪
How hard can it be?! I want him! I want him! I want him!
这有多难 我要抓住他 抓住他 抓住他
Stiltskin!
踩高跷皮儿!
I hear you're looking for me.
我听说你在找我
All right! Finally!
好了 总算来了
Who turned him in? Who gets the deal of a lifetime?
谁交出来了 谁能得到终身快乐合约
- I do. - What? But...
- 我 - 什么 但是...
If I'm turning myself in, I get the deal of a lifetime.
我把自己交出来了 我该得到终身快乐合约
That means you have to give me anything I want.
也就是说你要给我任何我想要的
No! Only true love's kiss can break your contract!
不 只有真爱之吻可以打破你的合约
So if you thought you were just gonna...
所以你要是以为你可以...
- in here and get your life back... - I'm not here to get my life back.
- 就这样 夺回你的生活 - 我来不是为了要夺回我的生活
Then what do you want?
那你想要什么
The ogres. They are all free.
绿怪们 他们都自由了
But where is Shrek?
不过史莱克呢
This is not good.
不太妙啊
I don't know. Not much of a storybook ending.
不知道 这不太像童话故事的结尾
The noble Shrek turns himself in to save a bunch of filthy ogres.
高尚的史莱克用自己换取了一群 肮脏绿怪的自由
All that matters is that they're free...
只要他们都自由
...and Fiona is safe.
而且菲奥娜是安全的
I bet Fiona would be really touched to hear that.
我确信菲奥娜会为此深深感动
But, hey...
但是 嘿
...I guess you can tell her yourself.
我觉得你可以亲口告诉她
Fiona!
菲奥娜!
Stiltskin, we had a deal! You agreed to free all ogres!
踩高跷皮儿 我们达成协议了的 你同意放了所有绿怪的
Oh, yeah.
是啊
But Fiona isn't all ogre, is she?
但菲奥娜不算真正的绿怪 不是吗
By day, one way, by night, another. Blardy, blardy, blar.
白昼与黑夜交替更迭 之类之类的
Nobody's smart but me!
没人比我更聪明了
That was a really brave thing you did, Shrek.
你真的很勇敢 史莱克
Thank you.
谢谢
No, you were right.
不 你说得对
I wasn't there for you.
你需要我时我不在
And not just at the Dragon's Keep, but...
不仅仅是在火龙看守的高塔 还有...
...every day since.
之后的每一天
Well...
好吧
...you're here now.
但你现在在这儿了
Let go of me! I have got to save Shrek!
放开我 我要去救史莱克
Don't be a fool, mule!
别傻了 驴子
She's right. Rumpel's palace is locked up tighter
她说得对 烂皮儿的宫殿守卫森严
- than Old Mother Hubbard's Cupboard. - And that cupboard wasn't guarded
- 比老外婆的抽屉还严实 - 至少抽屉没有
by a whole bunch of mean, ugly, nasty witches.
一群刻薄丑陋的女巫守卫着
Hey! We can hear you!
嘿 我们听得见的
Sorry!
不好意思
We must get into the palace.
我们必须进入宫殿
Man, Shrek and me just busted out of that place!
史莱克和我倒从里面出来过
But how?
但怎么进去
The same way we're gonna bust in.
怎么出来就怎么进去
Yay! My new pretty ball! Didn't it look bigger in the catalogue?
耶! 我的新球球 是不是比购物目录上的看起来还大些
I guess it'll have to do.
看起来很不错
Witches, finally, the moment we've all been waiting for.
女巫们 我们期待已久的时刻终于到来
The main event of the evening!
今晚隆重的盛事
I present Shrek and Fiona!
有请史莱克和菲奥娜
And now, to put the past behind us once and for all,
现在就让往事随风
I give you a princess's worst nightmare!
让我重新展示一场英雄救美的童话
Fiona's old flame, the keeper of the keep...
菲奥娜的噩梦 守卫者...
...Dragon!
火龙!
- Donkey? - And Puss!
- 驴子? - 和...
In Boots!
穿靴子的猫!
Get them, get them, witches!
抓住他们 抓住他们 女巫们!
Incoming!
小心
- Donkey, woo her! - Woo who?
- 驴子 求爱 - 向谁求爱
Your wife!
你老婆
Uh-oh.
啊哦
I'll call you! We're in love!
我会打给你的 我们相爱了
Fiona, hold on!
菲奥娜 抓住了
Hey, you!
嘿 你
- Chimichangas?! - Get 'em while they're hot!
- 烤香肠?! - 趁热吃!
Jump!
跳
Now!
现在!
The dragon goes under the bridge!
穿过桥下
Through the loop!
绕过火龙
And finally...
最终...
Into the castle!
抵达城堡
Run!
跑!
Foo!
飞
So long!
再见
Come on, Fifi, go!
走 飞飞 走!
Go! Witches, close up the floor!
女巫们 把门关上
Come on, Fifi, go! Flappity flap!
飞啊 飞飞 快 扇翅膀
Come on, go! Fly away! Up, up! Go!
快 走 飞 飞啊
Fifi, no!
飞飞 不
Victory is ours!
胜利是属于我们的
Looks like we're having curly-toed weirdo for breakfast.
似乎明天早餐又有新花样了
Hey, we make a pretty good team.
我们真是好搭档
You have no idea.
没想到吧
Shrek?
史莱克?
His day is up. His day is...!
他的末日到了 他要完了...
Shrek?
史莱克?
It's all right.
没事的
There has to be something I can do.
一定有什么我可以做的
You've already done everything for me, Fiona.
你已经为我做了所有了 菲奥娜
You gave me a home and a family.
你给了我家和家人
You have kids?
你有孩子?
We have kids.
我们有孩子
Fergus, Farkle and a little girl named...
费格斯 法科尔 还有个小女儿叫...
- Felicia. - Felicia.
- 费利西亚 - 费利西亚
I always wanted to have a daughter named Felicia.
我一直想生个女儿 取名费利西亚
And someday...
总有一天...
...you will.
你会有的
You know what the best part of today was?
你知道今天最美好的部分是什么吗
I got the chance to fall in love with you all over again.
我又重新爱上了你
Fiona, the sunrise!
菲奥娜 太阳升起了
You're still... an ogre!
你还是个...绿怪
- True love's form. - Impossible!
- 真爱之魂 - 不可能
The kiss worked.
吻生效了
What?!
什么?!
Fifi!
飞飞
Puss!
靴猫!
No, no, no!
不 不 不
No, not yet! I'm not ready! No, wait!
不 我还没准备好呢 等等
I love you, Daddy!
我爱你 爸爸
Shrek! Shrek! Shrek! Shrek!
史莱克! 史莱克! 史莱克! 史莱克!
Everybody, I have found another cake!
大家注意 我又找到了个蛋糕
Shrek? Are you OK?
史莱克? 你还好吗
Fiona. I've never been better.
菲奥娜 我从没感觉这么好过
Roar!
咆哮!
Happy Birthday, Farkle.
生日快乐 法科尔
Fergus, my little man!
费格斯 我的小家伙
And Felicia, sweetheart.
还有费利西亚 小甜心
I believe this is yours.
我想这是你的吧
Thank you, Daddy.
谢谢 爹地
Hey, Uncle Shrek! How about giving my babies an encore!
嘿 史莱克叔叔 给我的宝宝们再来一遍
Please, senor, let us have it!
求你了先生 再来一次吧
- I didn't know we could do that. - That's my best friend!
- 我从不知道我们还有这一招 - 真是我的好朋友
You know, I always thought
我一直以为是我
that I rescued you from the Dragon's Keep.
把你从火龙看守的高塔中救出来的
You did.
确实是啊
No. It was you that rescued me.
不 是你救了我
Yummy!
好吃的!